I heard a quote the other day that said,
"If you're an overachiever, the quality
of your life is determined by how you
answer the following question.
What's actually driving you?"
This stuck with me because most people
assume that ambition [music] is only a
positive thing. They think that having
underlying motivation to get [ __ ] done
is healthy. And while it can be, in 99%
of cases, there's a dark side to that
ambition. A negative fuel that drives
you.
Like a deep-rooted insecurity you
develop when growing up, or someone in
your life that you needed to prove
wrong.
And it keeps people stuck in an endless
cycle [music] of achieving a goal,
becoming immediately dissatisfied, and
searching for the next thing that makes
them happy. So, they never feel whole or
worthy.
This isn't going to be the typical type
of video you expect to see talking about
success. I want to talk about the
downsides that can come to it. The
people that you look up to have the life
that you want often aren't living the
life that you actually want behind the
scenes. You constantly ask yourself,
"How do I get where I want to be?" But,
you never look inside yourself and ask,
"Why do I feel like I need to get
there?"
>> So, when you were competing, what was
actually driving you?
>> What really pushed me beyond what was
normal to do was a feeling like I had to
do that. Like, it was my identity. It
was who I was. I needed that to be
enough. And therefore, if [music] I
didn't do it, it would feel like a death
to myself. And that's what drove me to
keep pushing so hard for so long.
>> So, when did you first notice that there
was something darker behind your
ambition?
>> I would probably say that 2018 moment
when I looked back after, and then going
to the next year Olympia, and Ian being
like, "So, I had a conversation with
you. Like, you know, like, this you
maybe should stop competing. Like, if
your health is telling you that you
shouldn't do this you're going to hurt
yourself, like maybe you actually
shouldn't. And I couldn't accept that. I
was like, "No, I'm going to keep
competing. This is all I really know."
And I was like, "Oh, wow. Like why would
it feel so hard for me to step away from
this?" And I started to question it then
without really understanding it.
>> [sighs]
>> It's a hard thing but cuz what made me
realize it was my health, which was
blatant if you hurt your health and you
can't get that back. But a lot of times
these things that drive you
I'm intentionally talking about the dark
side, but often the dark side puts you
into a challenging position where you're
forced to look at yourself to learn more
about yourself. So, it's not bad
inherently. I'm grateful that what drove
me to get somewhere wasn't good that got
me somewhere good. It's not just asking
yourself, "How do I get there?" but
reminding yourself to ask, "Why do I
feel like I need this?" And checking in
with yourself consistently because what
sustains you in the short term isn't
always going to.
>> Can you be happy with a
darker motivation?
>> I think you can be happy with a darker
motivation, but I heard this beautiful
quote the other day that was like one
way of finding joy was in doing more
things that bring you joy, and the other
[music] way was in finding more joy in
the things that you already do or in the
person that you already are. So, yes,
you can be happy,
but
it's going to be fleeting. It's going to
fade. Yes, you get that win. Yes, you're
going through You have these big
moments. It's amazing. But eventually it
you get old. You have an injury. Or the
day after the win, you're back down.
It's fleeting. You need more. It's like
an addiction. It's something where you
constantly need more. You never quite
get enough of that thing you need. So,
you can feel happy and joyous moments,
but it's not consistent. It's not
sustained. It's always going to be
needing more fuel. It's not a strong
foundation.
>> [gasps]
>> So, what were you actually trying to
prove back then?
>> I'll speak for myself, but everyone's
kind of in the same boat. We're trying
to prove that we are enough. It's kind
of like the overarching thing. But I
think sometimes a deeper question isn't
just what are you trying to prove, but
what are you trying not to feel. Being
able to not feel things made me a very
good bodybuilder. And what's even
funnier and ironically is I spoke
throughout my career that I was trying
to feel more. That's what I wanted to
want was to feel. But what I wanted was
to prove I was enough by winning. And
how I was winning was by not feeling.
And by avoiding things I needed to feel.
Usually it's either overachievement or
procrastination. It's the same answer.
You're trying not to feel something.
You're avoiding doing the thing because
there's something you don't want to feel
that you think is going to come as a
result of doing the thing. Or you keep
chasing more and doing more, keeping
yourself so busy because there's
something that you're running from that
you don't want to feel. The only way to
move through something is to be able to
feel it. So, while you're hanging out
distracted or procrastinating or busy
and overachieving and accomplishing six
Olympias, you're just altering your
ability to grow because you have to feel
those pains
and feelings of inadequacies [music] and
self-worth that you're avoiding.
>> [snorts]
[music]
>> Ooh.
>> How aware were you of all of that at the
time?
>> 0% at the beginning.
I feel like I had to step away from
competing to start to lose the value I
got from winning and the excitement to
start to lose the value I was bringing
to businesses and companies and
relationships and friendships and
followers and likes on social media. All
these things had to start fading for me
to be like, "Oh, wait. There's something
behind all that now that those are gone
and they're not growing and I'm not
getting something from it. There's
something coming up now." And instead of
me finding something else to Let me go
start another business. Let me go work
on this and do that to distract myself.
Sometimes the hardest thing to do for an
overachiever is just to sit and doing
nothing and feel the pain. So, we're
human. We're wired to avoid pain. Until
you make your
unconscious conscious will rule your
life and you'll call it fate. My
unconscious was the thing that didn't
want to feel because it was making me a
better bodybuilder. But, my conscious
mind was like, "Well, I want to want to
feel because I know that's the right
thing to do." And because of that
discrepancy, I wasn't truly aware of
what I was doing.
>> Why do you think
Why do you think negative motivation is
so common?
>> So what?
>> So common.
>> I think
everybody's gone through some [ __ ] at
the point at some point in their life.
They've all had some kind of thing they
needed as a child or something that was
missed that led them not feeling great.
We're not taught how to really
communicate about our emotions and share
things and be able to be there for each
other and heal things the way that we
should
because it's [ __ ] hard and no one's
ever going to be perfect. All of our
parents will make mistakes. I'm going to
make mistakes and parents of my kids
will grow up with some of the same
feelings. We're just not really taught
to do that. We're taught, "Hey, get on
social media. Look at this person. He
seems happy. He's made
$20 million and has a Ferrari. Oh, well,
maybe that will make me happy." Then you
get there if you're lucky and you're
like, "Why do I still feel miserable?"
Because that wasn't the answer, you
know? So, I definitely I'm a huge
believer that social media is [ __ ]
our world up
dramatically. So, I think the lies that
it sells cuz you don't know what's
really going on in someone else's life.
My UPS dude's a [ __ ] beauty. He's
been working the same drive for 30 years
and he's happy. I'm like, "That dude's
happy." I know some rich ass people who
aren't happy.
>> What did having that type of drive end
up costing you?
>> I feel like the most blatant cost is
probably just like
a delay in real personal growth
because when you're still putting
your effort into thinking something
outside of yourself is going to get you
somewhere, you're only delaying the
inevitable realization that that's not
real and then the growth that comes
after that. But, I think you see a lot
of famous athletes, celebrities, people
who
go through multiple marriages, ruin
relationships,
become addicts to alcohol or some kind
of crazy stuff because they're
constantly going through that and
seeking more. So, the cost only gets
greater the longer you stay in it, I
think. I feel like in the gym the cost
is often obvious or in the work. For me
it was a gymnast. Injuries that you push
through and pains that last way longer
than they should because you're not
focusing on what you should. But outside
the gym, it's it's that cost of
relationships. You know, to try and do
something great that's selfish, it takes
a lot of mental bandwidth.
If you're married, you have a partner,
they're inevitably carrying a through
weight because you're focused on
carrying all that other pressure of the
everything you're trying to accomplish.
Even when it comes to like recent
decisions that I was able to make like
moving from Florida out of there's, it
was great for me and it was great for
business and all these things, but at a
certain point, my family doesn't need
more money, more business, and more
accomplishments, more things. They need
connection. They need need. They want
presence. They need to be somewhere
where they're going to grow and set
roots and feel safe and comfortable.
That was one of the recent things that I
had to
>> [music]
>> pull myself out of selfishly maybe what
I felt comfortable in doing to put the
greater needs of the people I care more
about first.
>> Is there a specific low point from your
competition days
that you'd share?
>> I feel like in 2023,
and this is deeper in my documentary,
but I almost retired.
And then decided to come back for
another one because
my family was going through some stuff.
There were some personal things going
on. And then I tore my lat.
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> Found out Courtney was pregnant and all
this stuff was kind of happening in my
life and I remember just like being in
this super just low like what like I
need to quit. This is only hurting me.
All this stuff going on in my outside
life, I can't focus and give the
attention that it needs because I need
to just distract, compartmentalize, and
focus on winning this Olympia.
And I did that and I won that Olympia.
And then I was like, I need to retire.
Like this is enough for me. I'm done
competing. And then I went back and did
another one because I told myself I'm
going to just do it at X, Y, and Z. But
realistically, if I'm being really
honest with myself, it's cuz I was still
searching for something selfish that I
was going to get from it that I knew I
wasn't. So, then that led to me putting
myself back into that journey knowing I
shouldn't have been there. And I was in
and out of a lot of like
low moments where I lost a lot of
passion for competing and I still doing
it and felt like I had to and then and
it kind of been a little
big lost cycle.
Even after I retired, it was Maybe
there's not one big moment other than
like the moment I tore my lat in that
prep when I remember all the pressure I
was feeling just like
weighted me down. I just hit the ground
and started crying at the gym and I was
like, "Fuck dude, there's too much going
on in my life right now. I can't carry
this anymore."
But uh there was just a string of kind
of ups and downs since then where I've
been like
like I said earlier in this video when
you're trying to really uncover things
that you've been hiding from for a long
time, it hurts. The reason you've been
hiding from them is cuz painful to feel
these things. And by making yourself
feel those, it's kind of
maybe it's not one big moment, but it's
just this consistent feeling of like
you're tired no matter how much sleep
you get, you never feel rested. Your
mind's never really at ease. You're in
this constant state of tension. You're
not really you don't you know there's
these things you love to do, but you
don't have the ambition to do them
anymore. You're just doing the bare
requirement or routine and it becomes
this like fog of time that kind of goes
on and you're like, "Why am I doing
this?" And again, usually that fog is
just like a deeper part of your brain
that you're like, "I don't want to feel
these things." So, you just kind of numb
out from that. And you really have to
like force yourself to face all those
things.
>> [snorts]
>> What happened to your drive after your
body building career?
>> There was a little period that I'm still
kind of in and out of where I didn't
know why I was doing what I was doing or
where I was going. So, I just felt
everything I was doing felt really hard
to do. Like I felt like I was climbing
this uphill battle where these things I
used to enjoy and used to come naturally
to me felt more like a battle. And I
realized there's difference of like two
different types of growth that you have.
There's many more but just two I'm
thinking about. There's there's the one
where you can talk to about with a
friend and this is how I was thinking
about it. Where you see somebody, you
see a stranger and you're like, "I just
won another Olympia. I just my business
just got into Walmart. I just hit a
million followers on Instagram." Like
all these things you can talk about. And
then there's the like
I was more present with my family
because
I've been less stressed about trying to
win Olympia and getting six meals in a
day and recovering perfectly and getting
stronger every day. So, I was able to
enjoy a moment a little bit more and you
may not even realize it. No one else
will see it or understand it, but it's a
form of growth and it's a direction of
growth that I wanted to go and that was
important to me. But there's that subtle
difference of like the thing that you're
achieving to talk about to be like,
"Look what I did." Which is not the only
reason you do those things. I love
ambition. I'm still going to do [ __ ]
cool things. I still want to accomplish
more and do more.
But then there's that other type of
goal and growth where no one can really
see. Maybe your best friend spends some
time with you and they're like, "You're
something a little different about you.
There's a lighter piece of nature about
you." But the average person you can't
just tell them or post on Instagram
about what you accomplished.
>> How did becoming a dad change your
ambitions?
>> I think in that exact way. Being a dad
and I wish it happened immediately but
transparently I had Bradley and I still
did another Olympia so I was still
doing a more selfish pursuit. And again,
I'm not trying to talk about it in a
negative way. I'm just trying to talk
about the cost of these things in this
video. I still loved what I did. I
accomplished so much. Bodybuilding was
so amazing. It did so much for me in my
life and I'll always be grateful for it.
Getting Bradley to sleep through the
night or getting her to have a nap when
she hasn't had a nap in a month may not
be as exciting as glorious but I can
find a lot of joy and gratitude in that
because they're are I get to share only
with my wife and with the most important
things in my life, which is my family.
So, I think just priority shift,
a lot less selfless, and it's still a
journey I'm working on. You know, being
selfish is ingrained in my brain with
the body building, so I'm still working
on it, but at least open my eyes better.
>> What was it like to walk away from the
one thing that you built your whole life
around?
>> Hard.
Eye-opening.
Painful.
It was a big growth experience, for
sure. It just It showed me a lot of how
I
was conscious of the idea of not
building your identity around something
perishable, and yet I still did it,
because there was a grieving process
when I left it. And I think I fought it
more than I even should have, but I
think inevitably, especially when we're
young and trying to figure who we are,
we're going to attach it to the things
we're doing, especially the things we're
good at.
But the reality is that they are
perishable. They will leave one day. So,
you will experience a grief and a pain
if you attach yourself to something that
isn't going to last forever. And I
absolutely did that, so it was kind of
more of a rediscovering of who am I in
the absence of everything I used to
define myself. And I don't have the
answer yet, but I'm at least asking the
question now, and I'm looking in
different places than I was before,
which feels good.
Yeah.
Life is perishable, I guess, so you got
to keep actively working on the and that
you wouldn't care about.
>> [music]
[snorts]
[sighs]
>> It's one way to smoke your lower back.
Holy [ __ ]
What's driving you now if another trophy
isn't the goal?
Ultimately, a deeper desire to
understand myself,
both to fully let off the pressure and
allow myself to just
enjoy life without constantly needing
like I need to be and do more and to
give myself that peace that I believe
all people deserve,
and to make myself
into that man that I want to be who can
properly lead my family because
my family is ultimately now the greatest
part of my life that I want to make sure
that when I look back, I know I did all
the things I could do to be the best
version of myself for them.
What's your philosophy on
doing hard things when there's no trophy
and no reward at the end of it?
I think hard doing hard things in
general really allows you to see who you
really are. They show you They kind of
strip away the performance that you put
on for the world, and then you're
d- neck-deep in just who you are in face
of reality. And if there's not even
doing it for a reason, you're not like,
"Oh, least at the end of this I'm
getting this." It forces you to ask the
questions deeply, why am I doing this?
What's driving me? What's most important
to me? What matters to me? And it forces
you to ask a lot of questions, and I
think a lot of things in life in general
that are hard
are there to show you who you are.
There's another beautiful quote I love,
it's
life will always present you with people
and circumstances to show you where
you're not free.
So, even if you're going through
something hard, or you're doing
something hard, it's the circumstance
that is showing you, making you question
what can I not be with? Who am I? What's
important to me? And that really helps
you understand who you are.
>> What would you say to someone who's
driven but feels like that drive
is coming from the wrong place?
>> Don't beat yourself up.
I don't regret being driven by coming
from a place of insecurity,
or just coming from the wrong place if
you don't want to call it that. Call it
what you will, but I don't regret it cuz
it put me in the position that allowed
me to grow and to learn a lot about
myself, and I haven't figured it out.
I'm still working through these things,
but I'm just in a better place now. So,
don't beat yourself up. If it's working
and you're enjoying part of it, at least
you enjoy the ride, but just understand
that it's not going to keep you happy
forever.
But ask yourself,
do you really want to not be driven by
that anymore? Because the truth is that
coming from a healthy place doesn't make
you less ambitious. You can still be
extremely ambitious and accomplish
incredible things, but only if you
actually care about them.
So, you may be seeking something from
this business that's going to make you a
million dollars,
but you may not care about it. You may
get there and be miserable.
So, do you want that or do you want to
be happy? Would you rather be right or
would you rather be happy? And maybe
you're not ready to want to be happy.
Maybe you're like, "No, I just rather be
rich. [ __ ] being healthy." Cool. Just be
honest with yourself, you know? You
don't need to go on these journeys of
self-discovery or anything if you don't
want to. Just be honest with yourself
and try and at least ask yourself the
question enough times going through
being like, "You know what? I know I'm
kind of [ __ ] up and this is coming
from a hard place, but I don't care
right now. This is what I'm choosing to
do." At least you're consciously making
a decision. There's no wrong There's
nothing wrong. You never do anything
wrong in life. There's no wrong way of
doing things. There's stuff you want and
then you get it or you don't. Things
work or they don't. Not wrong, not bad.
You just don't want to be driven by
subconscious things and end up somewhere
you don't want to be. So, we've got to
ask yourself the hard questions.
>> What happens to the ambition itself when
the fuel changes?
>> It depends on the person. The ambition
can get significantly greater and
lighter cuz you feel like you're less
bogged down by the pressure of needing
to be something or do something. You can
actually feel lighter and have more
energy and have more ambition towards
it.
>> [music]
>> Or maybe it opens your eyes that you
never really cared about. Maybe it was
your dad or someone else that put this
goal on you that you felt like you
needed to do it and you never even
wanted it in the first place. And it
allows you to step away from it and from
the outside lose [music] ambition,
but it gives you energy to be able to
put into something that you really do
care about. So, it really depends on the
person. It depends on how you view and
define ambition. Is it ambition driving
towards more money or is it more peace
and more happiness?
Whatever it means to you is really
subjective.
>> Do you think you can get further
with ambition coming from a positive
motivation even though it might be more
challenging than to find that.
Depends on what you define as further.
If you
look at our current state of our
society's
definition of further or success, it's
probably more followers on Instagram, a
bigger business, more money, next year
house, and then you know, if that's what
you mean by further, it's very different
from
a deep feeling of self-love and being
proud of who you are and not feeling
like you need to be someone different,
being at peace with yourself, being
present day-to-day, not feeling like you
need more. You know, like these things
are so subjective, so it really really
depends, but I think when you're doing
something that's hurting yourself, like
if you're working like 100-hour weeks,
putting your health at risk, trying to
win more bodybuilding championships, and
you're doing all these things that are
hurting yourself,
I'll
probably made it further in my
bodybuilding career because I was coming
[music] from a healthy place, and had I
really been
more conscious, maybe I wouldn't have
even gotten six. Had I been less
conscious of what I wanted, maybe I
would have gotten seven. So, I think it
took me further
because it let me walk away from it
and not get seven, but choose to start
working on the hard things that are more
important to me.
Whereas someone else might be like, "Oh,
had you kept getting driven by that, you
could have gone to more Olympias, and
then you would have even been better."
You know, so it really again, I can't
answer these questions for anyone else
but for myself.
I think
come trying to come from a healthier
place has taken me further in what's
most important to me.
All right, that's a wrap on this. I
think a key thing to say is I don't
regret coming from the place that I did
and using that to drive me forward. I
just didn't want to let that drive me
forward forever. I'm grateful for my
journey, I'm grateful for who I am, and
for where I'm going. So, the whole trick
is just be honest with yourself and ask
yourself the hard questions don't just
run through life blindly.
Appreciate you guys watching. See you
next time.